本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
The era of Parsis, May 321 years.
パルス暦３２１年５月
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
Crown Prince Arslan left Peshavard fortress
王太子アルスラーンはペシャワール城を後にして
and he continued to lead his army,
王都エクバターナをルシタニア軍から奪還すべく
which should repel the Ekbanatu in Lyusitanii.
進軍を続けていた
Ten thousand horsemen
その第１陣　１万騎を率いるのは
アルスラーンが発令した檄文に応じてはせ参じた
They were those who took a written order signed by Arslan.
Son of Lord Munzir of the Oxus, the kingdom of Parsa, Zaravant
Zaravant, Esfan and Tus, young generals.
ザラーヴァント
The younger brother of the captain of cavalry from the kingdom Parsis Shapur, Esfan
イスファーン
トゥースの若き将たちである
commander of the garrison Zara kingdom Parsis, Tus
Army Arslan held not less than two hundred fasangov
アルスラーン軍は２００ファルサングもの距離を
in just five days.
僅か５日で駆け抜けたのである
kaze ga zawameki kudaketa kimochi
Quiet wind awakens emotions and broken,
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
misukashi teru you de furueta yo
I see through everything and I shiver.
michita tsuki no hi touboe no inochi
In the sky a full moon, and the city comes howling:
片源
Rei
时间轴
钦钦&雪糕
压制
Coolkid
mada oite kanaide yo
"Please do not throw until we have!"
bokura torikaeseru ka na iro tsuki no sora
Will we return to the old sky, painted in the colors?
hokori mamire no yume mai agete
Rise in the dance vortex hourglass Sci,
kobushi wo nigittanara
to be clamped in their fists.
ima hashire hashire tsuji kaze ni natte
Now run forward, run forward, and stand by the whirlwind,
rettou zetsubou issai fukitobashite iku
feelings of hopelessness and despair of sour cream on the way.
oikakenakya saigo no tobira
Clears the currently last track.
nando chittatte dai gyakuten
Let all break, we will rise again,
kono goe ga shagare tatte inorinouta todoketai yo
even a hoarse voice will sing songs and prayers.
tarinai bokura de shinji teta sekai wo ubaetara
Even insignificant, as we will be able to capture the whole world in which to believe.
madamada madamada make rarenai
We have still not yet been defeated!
Chapter XXII
News of the advancing army of Prince Arslan
アルスラーン王太子の進軍は
Giscard has reached the ears in the royal capital of Ecbatana.
王都エクバターナのギスカールの耳にも届いていた
Arslan forces accrue approximately sixty thousand people.
アルスラーンの軍勢は　その数６万と称し
They went through the forest Chassum
チャスーム城を越え　大陸公路を堂々と西へ進軍しています
and boldly directed to the west of the continental way.
Most likely, the number of the army called
おそらくは　我らを威圧するために兵の数を多く触れているにすぎず
exaggerated to scare us.
We can assume that in fact there are thirty or forty thousand will.
実際は３～４万といったところが妥当ではないかと思われます
Immediately gather the troops stationed in Ecbatana,
早急にエクバターナ駐屯の兵をまとめ　１０万の部隊を編制しろ
and to mobilize an army of a hundred thousand.
With all due respect, Prince Giscard,
恐れながら　ギスカール様
Are we send a hundred thousand men against thirty or forty thousand of the enemy?
３～４万の敵に１０万もの兵を出す必要がありましょうか
It is not easy to prepare as many people to war.
その数の兵を動かすのは容易ではござらん　故に…
Then...
It looks like you do not understand anything.
何も分かっておらぬな
What if they have something in mind?
それがヤツらの策だったらどうする
Army with the average amount may suffer damage.
中途半端な数では　かえって被害を大きくするやもしれん
And with a hundred thousand, we defeat the enemy in one fell swoop!
１０万の兵をもって敵を一気にたたく
His Highness said is true.
王弟殿下の仰せのとおりだ
The enemy has a strategy Narsus.
敵軍にはあの策士ナルサスがいる
If you believe the rumors, only play into his hands.
うわさを信じれば　ヤツの思うつぼ
I have just returned.
ただいま帰還いたしました
Well, well, Mr. Silver mask.
これはこれは　銀仮面卿
We reported to you
ザーブル城攻略戦においては　随分な働きをされたと聞き及んでおります
excellently coped with the capture of the castle of Zabul.
Just as they say, you are unable to catch their leader, the high priest Bodin?
ですが　首謀者である大司祭ボダンを取り逃がしたとか
Failed?
逃がした？
What's so funny?!
何がおかしい
To hear such words from the sycophants of His Highness ...
王弟殿下のご機嫌取りがよく言う
What?!
何を
Enough!
やめよ
Bodine has no role to Lyusitanii.
もはやルシタニアにとって　ボダンなど取るに足らぬ者
I decided to just let him go.
あえて捨て置いたまでです
What is more important,
それより　ザーブル城より戻った我が軍は今３万弱
my army, returned from Zabul castle now charges about thirty thousand.
If you lend seventy thousand soldiers Lyusitanii,
ルシタニア兵を７万お借りできれば
You see for yourself how Arslan's army fall by force of a hundred thousand people.
１０万で一気にアルスラーン軍を討ち取ってみせますが
Good.
よかろう
Then...
では
Wait.
待て
I'm not saying that you trust the life of seventy thousand men.
７万の兵の命をお主に預けたわけではない
Only I borrow, and all.
あくまでも貸しただけだ
Do not forget that.
そのことを忘れるな
I understand completely.
心得ております
Until I come back with the head Andragorasa offspring,
アンドラゴラスの小せがれの首を携えて戻るまで
I hope you listen to your mind.
心健やかにお待ちいただければと
There, in front of a tavern, where many soldiers.
この先に兵士たちが集まってる酒場があるようだ
Learn all there is?
そこで情報を
Yes.
ああ
おい　お前ら　そこで何をこそこそしている
Hey you. What are you hiding there?
Suspicious ...
怪しいな
We're running away to get married!
私たち　駆け落ち中なんです
What?
Good men, you listen.
兵隊さん　聞いてくださいよ
He said he did not throw me to the death,
死ぬまで絶対に離れないって言ったくせに
and now the nerves took over,
この人ったら　やっぱり帰ろうなんて臆病風を吹かせてるんですよ
and he says that we have to go back!
You do not really love me, huh ?!
私のこと　本当に愛してないのね
あ　あ…愛しているとも
I-I-I love you!
You do not doubt my love for you!
僕の愛に一点の曇りもない
True? I can trust you?
ほんと　信じていいのね
Of course!
もちろんさ
Cute!
あんた
愛してるよ　一生離さない
Going together!
Forget about them.
好きにしろ
I will not let you go!
And I love you!
私も愛してるわ
僕は幸せだ
I'm lucky!
Hey! You'll be a long time to squeeze me ?!
ちょっと　いつまで抱きついてる気
You do clung to me!
抱きついてきたのはそっちだろ
いや　しかし　参ったな
Yes, right now it is not easy.
参ったよな
大丈夫か
Drink more!
もっと飲め　もっと飲め
ほら　ほら　ほら
Come on! Come on!
Today I'm buying!
今日は俺のおごりだ
Guys, get drunk till you drop!
みんな　じゃんじゃん飲んでくれ
Yes!
Heck. These miserable remnants of Parsis goes too far.
調子に乗りやがって　パルスの残党が
They imagined themselves as heroes because of what took Zabul castle.
ザーブル城攻略成功で　すっかり英雄気取りだぜ
I heard they will command
進軍してきているパルス軍をたたくのもヤツらに指揮させるらしいぜ
Even in the battle with the approaching army Parsis.
Saam Zande?
サームにザンデか
Winners us. Why do we have to fight under them ?!
なんで戦勝国の俺たちがヤツらに使われにゃならんのだ
Quiet, quiet.
まあ　まあ
But their strength is forty or fifty thousand, right?
だけど　ヤツら４～５万の軍勢なんだろ
What sense to send them a hundred thousand?
それを１０万でたたくってどういうこった
ギスカール様に考えがあるらしい
The Prince Giscard's plans, it seems.
Come on! We continue! More booze!
ほら　もっとどんどん飲めよ
Soldiers lyusitaniantsy, do not hesitate! Join now!
ルシタニアの諸君も遠慮なくやってくれ
でかい面しやがって
Here are the upstarts.
Like this! Come on, drink more!
いいぞ　ほら　もっと飲め
Yes! Like this! Go on!
おお　そうだ　もっとやれ
So, the enemy is sending a hundred thousand people ...
敵は１０万の兵で進軍してくる…か
And so what?
それが何さ
Mr. Narsus really took the initiative cunning.
確かにナルサス様の策は先手を打った
But the enemy, too, does not relax.
だが　敵もさる者だ
Hey, what are you all?
ちょっと　何それ
You underestimate my Narsusa?
私のナルサスにケチをつける気
When he became "yours"? Do not make me laugh.
いつ　お前のになった　ふざけるな
He's my Narsus!
私のナルサスよ
My lord Narsus!
私のナルサス様だ
This problem children.
これだから　お子様は
What do you need?
なんの用だ
Tomorrow I go to war.
明日　出陣する
I wonder how your son appreciates your life?
果たして　お前の息子がどの程度お前の命を思っているのだろうな
I do not want to upset,
あいにくだが
but I have not fallen so low that I needed his help.
あやつに命のともし火をつないでもらうほど　俺は落ちぶれてはおらん
And you?
お主こそ　薄汚いルシタニアの手を借りて
Accept help from the vile lyusitaniantsev,
この俺を玉座から引きずり下ろし
and robbed me of the throne.
And you did not tell me that you have some kind of a crazy idea,
よもや　それを己の名誉などと血迷ったことを考えてはおらぬだろうな
which will justify your actions?
What?
何
You do not understand anything.
お主は何一つ分かってはおらぬ
What are you?
なんのことだ
Our royal family Parsis of mixed blood ...
我ら血塗られたパルス王家の系譜
What are you taldychu?
何を言っている
All according to the prophecy.
予言どおりだ
Prophecy?
予言？
All the way in the prophecy.
全ては予言どおり
the fate of the mechanism continues to rotate.
運命の歯車は回っているにすぎん
Only you that do not know anything.
お前が知らぬだけのこと
I do not think you've defeated me, kid.
このわしに勝ったと思うなよ　小僧
今度ここに来るときは　土産に貴様の息子の首を持ってきてやろう
When I come here next time,
in my hand is a souvenir of your son's head.
At this time I'm going to bury this brazen Daryuna!
今度こそ　あの傲慢なダリューンを墓穴へ放り込んでくれるわ
Prince Hermes,
ヒルメス殿下
アルスラーン軍を打ち倒した暁には
we will crush the army of Arslan,
please, crush enemies in the royal capital
この王都にはびこる敵を蹴散らし　王位におつきください
and take the throne.
I already know.
言うまでもない
そうか
Clear.
あえて兵の数を少なく触れ回っておいて　相手の裏をかくつもりだったが
I have deliberately decided to conceal the true number of our troops,
and outwit the enemy, but it seems they are not stupid.
その上をいったか
ギスカールという男もなかなかやる
Giscard did not miss this.
１０万か…
One hundred thousand...
数では劣ることになるな
In terms of numbers, we are inferior to them.
Uh-huh.
それと
And yet, among the survivors parsiantsev
パルスの残党の中には　サームという武将がいるようです
General has called Saam.
サームが
Yield ?!
知り合いですか
Do you know him?
名将と誉れ高いお方だ
A well-known outstanding commander.
敵にはしたくない相手だな
No one wishes to have it at enemies.
父上のために随分と働いてくれていた
He previously was ready to do everything for the sake of my father.
During the Battle of Atropatena he stayed in the castle in order to protect my mother.
アトロパテネの折は　母上の護衛として城に残っていた
そのサームが　なぜ…
Now Saam ... Why?
こちらも　それ相応の策をもって当たらねばなりませんな
We will go into battle with the plan, where everything will be taken into account.
Narsus, I am counting on you.
ナルサス　頼んだぞ
お任せあれ　殿下
Be calm, Prince.
策士の名誉に懸けて　ここ一番の戦略を練りましょうぞ
Rely on my reputation,
I will work out the best plan for the final battle!
上
Top!
中
Centre!
下
Below!
強くあらねば　私自ら力をつけなければならない
I have to become stronger.
It should be as much as possible.
やはり　まだまだだな
Still, I still have a lot to learn.
そんなことはございません
Far from it.
たくましくなられております
You have grown up.
それに　君主が目指すべきは武勲ばかりではございません
Also,
not for feats of arms should try ruler.
ああ
Yes.
いずれにしても　私はもっと自分を磨かなければならない
And yet, I still have many of the necessary work to get better.
そして　皆が誇れる王を目指したいのだ
And I want to be a king who will all be proud of.
はい
Yes.
どうした　みんな
What's up, guys?
も…申し訳ありません
P-forgive us.
お二人の剣の扱いに見とれてしまって
We were just staring at your fight.
失礼しました
Sorry.
ちょっと待ってくれ
Wait!
ダリューン
Darjun.
そなたに頼みがある
I need to ask you something.
もっと腰を入れて
Hip work!
はっ
There is!
利き腕は後ろだ
Dominant hand behind!
はっ
There is!
弓を射るときは　まず上半身を一直線にするよう　背中を伸ばすことだ
When you are shooting with a bow,
first you need to straighten your upper body.
やってみろ
Try.
はい
Yes.
いや　そうではない
No not like this.
なるほどな
Clear.
新たに加わった兵士に武器の扱いを教えてやってくれとは　殿下らしい
He asked to train newcomers,
how to handle a gun ...
In the spirit of the Prince.
ああ
Yes.
いよいよ　ヒルメス王子と戦うことになるな
In the end, we will fight with the prince Hermes.
案ずることはない
No need to worry.
殿下は見かけより　はるかに強く　広い心をお持ちだ
Prince is much stronger and more generous than it seems at first glance.
確かに　覚悟を決めたとおっしゃっておられた　だが…
Yes, he said that he found the determination. But...
お前まだ　殿下がヒルメス王子に王位を譲るのではとか考えているのか
You still think you can pass the throne to Prince
Prince Hermes, right?
もし　そうなったとして　お前はヒルメス王子に仕えるのか
If this happens, you will serve the prince Hermes?
冗談を言うな
Do not Bring nonsense!
だったら信じよう　我らの主を
Then we believe in our lord and ruler.
ああ
Yes.
ナルサス　よいか
Narsus I come in?
はい
Yes?
I interrupted.
邪魔をしたな
いえいえ　殿下
What are you, Prince.
ちょうど　ひと息入れようと思っていたところです
I just thought to take a break.
えっ　こ…これは
Uh, it's ...
静物画を
Still life.
いや…　相変わらず　すごい…
No ... As always, amazing.
で　どうなさいました
AND? What's the matter?
今日　兵たちの武芸の稽古を見ていて　一つ感じたことがあった
Today, I watched the soldiers training
and I felt something.
ほう　何をお感じになりましたか
What do you fall?
歩兵たちのことだ
This applies to the infantry.
最初こそ戸惑っていた様子だったが
At first they were unsure,
やがて皆　意気揚々と稽古に励んでいた
but with time,
themselves took up the training firm and proud.
というところでしょうか
This speech?
なぜ分かった
As you understood?
歩兵は皆　奴隷の身であった者たちです
All the Marines were once slaves.
おそらく武芸の稽古をすることなど　なかった者ばかりでしょう
Most likely, none of them had the opportunity to receive military training.
ああ　そのようだった
Yes, å at it.
だから　皆　嫌がって参加してくれないかとも思った
Therefore, I thought that they can refuse to participate.
戦は厳しく　そこには犠牲が付き物だ
War is cruel, and it is not without victims.
今回の戦では　たくさんの命が失われるだろう
In this battle could lose many lives.
だが　できるならば　私はもう兵士に命を落としてもらいたくない
But if possible, I would like to see more, none of the soldiers was killed.
それで　みんなに稽古に参加しないか誘ってみたのだ
So I invited all to train.
そうでしたか
Here's how.
人は皆　己が何者であるのか　どこへ進むのか
People always ask themselves who they are and where they are going.
その答えを求めて生きていくものだと私は思います
And I believe that we are living just to find answers to these questions.
ですが　与えられたことをするしかない奴隷たちは
But the slaves who could only perform tasks assigned to them,
その気持ちさえ　なくしている
even forgotten about this feeling.
今日　稽古に参加した彼らにとって　武芸を習うことは
Today people who participated in the training, learn to fight,
己のために己の意思で決めたこと
themselves have decided to do it on their own.
ただ何も考えず　従属しているだけの生き方ではなく
Rather than living mindlessly following orders only,
一人の人間として生きることを実感できた瞬間だったはずです
at some point they will want to feel,
what it means to live as an independent person.
彼らが何者であるか　そしてどう進むかを
You could say that you, Prince, to show them who they are
殿下がお示しになったといっていいでしょう
and which way they should go.
私が…
I...
まだ気がかりなことがおありですか
You something else bothering you?
いや　それにしても　お主とダリューンにはいつも助けられてばかりだ
No.
But I'm still helping you with Daryunom.
殿下には玉座についていただかないと　私の夢もかないませんゆえ
You must ascend to the throne,
otherwise my dream come true.
よもや　お忘れになってはおられないですよね
You do not forget that, right?
お主を宮廷画家とするということであろう
You that I will make you a court painter?
もちろん　忘れてはおらぬ
Of course, not forgotten.
Then I will be glad to serve you.
ならば　よろしくお願いいたします
そうだ
Exactly!
「決戦前夜」という題名で
I thought, call now
ダリューンに肖像の一つでも描いてやろうかと思いますが
"The night before an important battle" and draw a portrait Daryuna!
それは…　どうだろうな
Well, I do not know...
Tut kak-to quiet it?
やっぱり　なんか静かよね
確かに
And it is true.
ギーヴ様がいないからか
Probably because Mr. Gieva not.
そっか…
Just ...
ねえ　さみしくないの　ファランギースは
O, teʙe odinoko, Farangis?
なぜ私が寂しがることがある
Why should I be lonely?
だって　いい雰囲気だった…　じゃない
But you're so good with him ... or not?
バカな
Nonsense.
ただ…
Only...
ジンが言っている
Jin says ...
あやつの魂はここにあると
his spirit is here with us.
What?! That is, he died ?!
死んだってこと
まさか
What are you.
Even if he is killed, he still would not die now, huh?
あいつは殺されても　死ぬようなヤツではなかろう
確かにね
That's for sure.
遠く離れておっても　ヤツの心が殿下と共にあるということじゃ
Perhaps he is now far away,
but the heart of it with the Prince. Here's what I mean.
Castle of Emmanuel
聖マヌエル城
Castle of Emmanuel.
その名はルシタニアの歴史上の聖職者より取ったもので
So it called lyusitansky monk-historian.
パルス軍が長らく放置していた砦を
Fortress has long abandoned parsiantsami.
ルシタニアが侵攻の際　修復して拠点としたものである
When Lyusitaniya invaded there,
it was restored and made the citadel.
現城主は有徳の人　バルカシオン伯爵である
Now she manages a virtuous man,
Chart Barkasion.
Lord Holy Emmanuel, Barkasion castle
バルカシオン伯爵様
Lord graph Barkasion!
なぜ　パルスの兵が城内に入ることをお許しになるのです
Why did you let the soldiers enter the Parsa to the castle ?!
騒々しいな　エトワール
As rasshumelsya, Etoile.
たった今　イノケンティス陛下の勅令が届いたところだ
I just received a Royal Decree of His Majesty King Innosentisa.
陛下の？
From the King ?!
「パルス　ルシタニア連合軍１０万で
General strength and Parsis Lyusitanii a hundred thousand people
ここ聖マヌエル城でアルスラーン軍を迎え撃つ
clashed with Arslan's army here in castle of St. Emmanuel.
その指揮は銀仮面卿が執ることになった」と
And command them to Mr. Silver mask.
銀仮面卿…
Silver mask ...
ここから一歩たりとも敵軍を進ませてはならぬと仰せだ
We can not allow the enemy went on.
That is an order.
それは分かっております
I understand it.
ですが　なぜ異教徒の力を借りなければならないのです
But why should we take help from the Gentiles?
エトワール
Etoile, do not you think that this could be another test,
これもイアルダボート神の試練と受け止めることはできぬのか
God has prepared for us Ialdabaoth?
ですが…
But...
よいな
All clear?
分かりました
I understood.
これも試練なのか
This is also a test?
予言どおりだ
All according to the prophecy.
予言など…取るに足らぬ
Tiny prophecy ...
It does not play a role.
いよいよだな
Then came the hour.
はい
Yes.
ええ
Right.
必ず…パルス王国　王都エクバターナを
we will certainly
refund the royal capital of Ecbatana,
この手で奪還する
and I personally see to it!
YakuSub Studio
kimi ga deatta kokoro wa kitto
All the souls that you could meet on the way,
translation Mu_Cool
hitotsu datte machigai janai
certainly it was pure and innocent,
Editorial Mu_Cool
onaji yume wo daite
We kept the same dream.
Making Weekend
michi wo tagaeta hito wo omotta
People walking different paths,
nozarashi no akogare wo kakagete susumu kouya
killed all my hopes and desires revive again.
hohoemi mo sono namida mo
Smile on his face, tears running down her cheeks,
koko ni suteteyukenai kara
If you want to go ahead, they should not be forgotten.
kage wo daite shiroku takaku
Covered by the shadow of the summer, so white and immense,
namonaki boku to kimi no hata
our with you nameless flag flies.
mada hatenaku tsudzuku kono mich ino kanata ni
There, on the road, which extends an endless path,
tatta hitotsu no hikari wo sen no kokoro ni
There is one bright light, and with it a thousand souls.
miageru sora wo shinjiteru
Believe in the sky above his head,
michibiku hoshi wo higashi no takami ni sashishimesu yo
there putevodnaâ our star in the east, ee do not engage.
yume wa kono te de kanaeru
And their cherished dream in flesh forces.
黒衣の騎士は　くすんだ銀色の刃によって
Holding the dusky silver sword, a knight in black
鮮紅色の弧を宙に描いた
He drew a bright scarlet arch in the air.
次回　聖マヌエル城の攻防
Next time: "The battle for the Holy Emmanuel castle."
Chapter XXIII
少年は　そして王となる
And so the guy would be King.